<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A heartie prayer, in a needfull time of trouble. The sermon preached at Theobalds, before his Maiestie, and the lords of the Priuie Councell, an houre before the death of our late soueraigne King Iames. On Sunday, March 27. / By D. Price, deane of Hereford, then in attendance, and now chaplaine in ordinarie to his Maiestie.</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115208</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850427</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850427</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15629</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10047)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1528:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A heartie prayer, in a needfull time of trouble. The sermon preached at Theobalds, before his Maiestie, and the lords of the Priuie Councell, an houre before the death of our late soueraigne King Iames. On Sunday, March 27. / By D. Price, deane of Hereford, then in attendance, and now chaplaine in ordinarie to his Maiestie.</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Flesher, for Iohn Grismand, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Gun in Paules Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: The sermon at Theobalds, an houre before the death of King Iames.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Death and burial --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15629:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15629:1"/>
            <p>A HEARTIE PRAYER, In a needfull time of trouble.</p>
            <p>THE SERMON Preached at <hi>THEOBALDS,</hi> before his Maieſtie, and the Lords of the Priuie Councell, an houre before the Death of our late Soueraigne KING IAMES. <hi>On Sunday,</hi> March 27.</p>
            <p>By D. PRICE, Deane of <hi>Hereford,</hi> then in Attendance, and now Chaplaine in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie to his MAIESTIE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IER. 30.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Alas for that day <hi>was</hi> great, ſo that none <hi>was</hi> like it: it <hi>was</hi> euen the time of <hi>IACOBS</hi> trouble, but he <hi>is</hi> ſaued out of it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by M. FLESHER, for IOHN GRISMAND, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Signe of the Gun in <hi>Paules</hi> Alley. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15629:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15629:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS <hi>MAIESTIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Oyall <hi>Maſter:</hi> Your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious aſpect to my poore endeuors, often preſented in your <hi>religious</hi> preſence, hath encouraged mee to this Dedication of my <hi>laſt</hi> ſeruice to your bleſſed Father; and <hi>firſt,</hi> to your Maieſtie: for the whole world hath no greater Patronage of goodneſſe, then your ſelfe: and our daily bread, and hourely breath ſerueth vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Almightie, that you long be the gracious Patrone and Patterne of Religion.</p>
            <p>That I preſume to offer it vnto your Maieſtie, in this time of our
<pb facs="tcp:15629:3"/>iuſt cauſe of ioy, wherein the <hi>Lillies</hi> and <hi>Roſes,</hi> the <hi>Oliue</hi> and <hi>Vine,</hi> are conioyned; I excuſe it by the Pattern I ſee in Mount <hi>Thabor,</hi> wherein our bleſſed Sauiour, when he ſhewed his Diſciples a glympſe of his glory in his Transfiguration; hee ſeaſoned their Soules, rapt vp in thoſe vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioyes with the remembrance of his Paſsion: What this is, is like <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin,</hi> the birth of ſorrow, and of ſo much ſorrow to me, as had almoſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred my Soule from my Body. The <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>Heauen</hi> that hath wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped away our teares, keepe vs long and long from ſuch occaſion of tears, and Crowne your <hi>Royall Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Gracious Queene,</hi> with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Goodneſſe; which is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall Prayer</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>of your Maieſties moſt humble Chaplaine,</hi> DANIEL PRICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15629:3"/>
            <head>The Sermon at Theobalds, an houre before the death of King <hi>IAMES.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 118.25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Saue now I beſeech thee, O Lord: O Lord, I beſeech thee ſend now proſperitie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt <hi>fruits</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> are <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Sorrow;</hi> and euer ſince <hi>Sinne</hi> brought in <hi>Death, Death</hi> the lodge of all mens liues, driueth out <hi>Sinne,</hi> and <hi>triumpheth</hi> ouer <hi>Sinners.</hi> Looke on the foure firſt <hi>Fathers</hi> of the World; <hi>Adam</hi> ſignifieth earthy; <hi>Abel,</hi> mourning vanitie; <hi>Enoſh,</hi> ſorrow; <hi>Kenan,</hi> lamentation: and euer ſince, all times and all places, were and are (as this time and place, repreſenteth vnto vs) a <hi>time</hi> of <hi>mortalitie.</hi> and a Region of death in the ſhadow of Death, <hi>Nonne haec eſt regio mortuorum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr.</note> 
               <hi>vbi vmbra mortis, janua mortis, vincula mortis, &amp; corpus mortis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The preſent <hi>Cloud</hi> wherein wee are <hi>inueloped,</hi> and ſtand all as an <hi>amazed</hi> poore flocke of ſheep,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15629:4"/>beholding a ſauage <hi>Wolfe</hi> worrying our Royall Shepheard; looking vpon the <hi>wreſtling</hi> of our Royall <hi>Iacob,</hi> he that is <hi>ſpiritus oris noſtri, Chriſtus Domini,</hi> the very breath of our noſtrils, the Lords Anointed, now in Combat with the laſt enemy that ſhall be deſtroyed; the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it ſtriketh vs with a terrible terrour: our <hi>ſighes,</hi> &amp; <hi>teares,</hi> and <hi>prayers</hi> witnes it; and <hi>vnleſſe the tender mercy of our God, whereby the day ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth from on high, doe now viſit vs, to giue light to vs that ſit in darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death,</hi> wee ſhall finde, that our ſtrange neglect of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> the <hi>Lords day,</hi> doth portend our fatall flight vpon this <hi>Sabbath</hi> day. But <hi>Lord,</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall become of vs the poore ſheepe of thy paſture, O looke vpon thy <hi>Royall</hi> Seruant, O hide not thy face from thine Anointed: ſaue now, and heare our gratious Soueraigne, <hi>O King of heauen, now hee calleth on thee:</hi> now that the <hi>Angell</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> ſtrugleth with him, let the <hi>Angell</hi> of the <hi>Couenant</hi> bleſſe him; and as the <hi>Angell</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> ſtriueth with him, ſo let the <hi>Angell</hi> of the <hi>Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> ſtriue for him, and free <hi>his pretious ſoule</hi> from all paine, all ſorrow, all aduerſitie, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to thy diuine Maieſtie without ſpot or wrinckle. <hi>O Lord God ſaue our King, mercifully heare vs now we call vpon thee, Pitifully behold the ſorrowes of our hearts, Fauorably with mercy heare our prayers, Both now and euer, vouchſafe to heare vs O Chriſt, Gratiouſly heare vs O Chriſt, gratiouſly heare vs O Lord Chriſt. O Sonne of God, O Lambe of God, that takeſt away the ſinnes of the world,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15629:4"/>mediate with thy bleſſed Father, if it bee poſsible that this cup may paſſe from him, or elſe that his gratious ſoule may be bound vp in the bundle of life, to liue for euermore with thee in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> it was the <hi>ſtyle</hi> of <hi>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> for <hi>Royall</hi> Perſonages, <hi>Alas, Alas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 22.18.</note> for that noble Prince, wee may take vp that <hi>Alas, Alas.</hi> How lately haue wee celebrated <hi>Dauids diem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lennitatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 77.2.</note> our ſacred Soueraignes <hi>Inauguration?</hi> on which day,<note place="margin">Thurſday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties death.</note> hee that crowneth the <hi>yeare with good things,</hi> crowned the Crowne of our Head, our <hi>Royall</hi> King, with an eſpeciall <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> in manifeſting <hi>his heartie</hi> and <hi>deuout</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant truth, which hee had liued in, and maintained, and reſolved to dye in, deſiring vs all that were preſent, to beare witneſſe, ſealing that reſolution with the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament:</hi> after which diuine <hi>repaſt,</hi> his <hi>ſoule</hi> was ſetled in ſo ioyfull a <hi>repoſe,</hi> as that all worldly <hi>content</hi> could not compare with it. But <hi>Alas,</hi> that day, <hi>dies ſolennitatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.3.</note> is become <hi>dies tribulatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis:</hi> and as <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpake,<note place="margin">Lam. 2.22.</note> in this <hi>ſolemne day our terrours are round about vs: and this Lords day is the day of the Lords anger.</hi> And therefore let euery ſorowfull and faithfull heart, pray <hi>heartily,</hi> and cry <hi>mightily</hi> into heauen, <hi>Saue now I beſeech thee O Lord: O Lord I beſeech thee ſend now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We need not now to call for <hi>Sorrow</hi> before ſhe come, it is now the time that the Church hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted to eate the <hi>ſowre hearbs</hi> of <hi>repentance in Lent,</hi> that we may the more ſauourly reliſh the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15629:5"/>ſweet <hi>Paſſover</hi> of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> it is the ſpirituall <hi>Seed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time</hi> which ought to bee <hi>wateriſh,</hi> and wee are wont to be content with a <hi>wet Spring,</hi> to be ſure of a <hi>ioyfull Harueſt.</hi> Our true ſorrow is <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an <hi>after-wit,</hi> and <hi>after-wiſdome,</hi> wherein when wee ſee, how we haue <hi>betraid</hi> our ſelues into the hands of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> we may iuſtly wiſh that the <hi>Heauens</hi> aboue would weepe with vs, the <hi>Earth lament,</hi> the Rocks <hi>rend,</hi> the Mountaines <hi>eccho groanes,</hi> and riuers run with <hi>teares:</hi> and indeed I had proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Gods <hi>good hand,</hi> ſuch a portion of <hi>food</hi> for this daily bread, and would haue endeavored by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> to haue watered this <hi>Gedeons fleece</hi> with that <hi>deaw of Heauen.</hi> For as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the <hi>Temple,</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> of Gods Church, calleth it,<note place="margin">Ezek. 48.35.</note> 
               <hi>Iehovah Shammah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the Lord is there; So all our <hi>Prayers</hi> and preaching are onely to ſtir vp theſe <hi>graces</hi> of God in your holy <hi>deuotion</hi> and <hi>conuerſation,</hi> that your <hi>light</hi> may ſhine before <hi>men,</hi> to ſtop the <hi>mouths</hi> of any <hi>interloping Prieſt,</hi> or Ieſuited <hi>Proſelyte,</hi> that commeth to pry and ſpy, that he may ſee, that this place is, <hi>Iehovah ſhammah,</hi> the Lord is here, though he doth not know it. But as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was called by an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> in a <hi>Viſion,</hi> when about to goe to <hi>Bythinia,</hi> one of <hi>Macedonia appeared</hi> vnto him, and ſayd, <hi>O Paul come and helpe vs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 16.9.</note> ſo when my <hi>intentions</hi> were ſetled on <hi>meditations</hi> of <hi>repentance,</hi> the ſad face of this <hi>ſorrowfull</hi> family <hi>repreſented</hi> it ſelfe vnto me, and diuers <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>Concluſion</hi> of this text, begun on <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15629:5"/>laſt, vnto which <hi>ſudden</hi> motion I the rather yeelded, becauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> had taught me, &amp; <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged</hi> me in that confidence, that hee that <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euery good worke, will performe it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>and perfit it vnto the day of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The Text is like that <hi>Petition</hi> in the Lords Prayer, <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue, Sola petitio orationis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicae cum repetitione.</hi> There be two twins in the wombe of my Text.<note place="margin">Gen. 38.30.</note> 
               <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Zarah</hi> were twins, but they were of an inceſtuous birth.<note place="margin">Gen. 24.22.</note> 
               <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> were twins, but there was a battle betweene them in the wombe before they were borne; but theſe two twins, two petitions, are like <hi>Eſayes</hi> two <hi>Zeraphins</hi> ſinging one with the other: or like two fiery <hi>Cherubins</hi> taking wing together, and flying vp to heauen, in a needfull time of trouble, to ſeeke diuine aſſiſtance. In this later <hi>Petition,</hi> obſerue plainly as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, 1. <hi>Cui,</hi> to whom it is directed, <hi>Lord.</hi> 2. <hi>Quis,</hi> the perſon who it is by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is vttred, <hi>I.</hi> 3. <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo,</hi> the manner how earneſtly inplored, <hi>Lord I beſeech thee, I beſeech thee.</hi> 4. <hi>Quid,</hi> the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſuit ſo required, <hi>Lord I beſeech thee ſend proſperity.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Quando,</hi> the time ſo vrgently, inſtantly importuned; <hi>Lord I beſeech thee ſend now proſperity.</hi> The ſad <hi>preſence</hi> and repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this <hi>day,</hi> delighteth not in deſcant. Our <hi>Royall</hi> Maſter is in his ſad <hi>Paſsover,</hi> and my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations ſhall keepe the <hi>Paſsover;</hi> The Lord Ieſus who was our true <hi>Paſsover,</hi> be preſent with vs.</p>
            <p>It was a wiſe ſpeech, <hi>Iuſtin</hi> Martyr doth cite
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15629:6"/>out of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> in his booke <hi>de Monarchia,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, If any ſhall ſay, I am God, beſides that onely one God, let him create and make another world like to this, that we may <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue</hi> him. And <hi>Tully</hi> in his 2. booke <hi>de legibus,</hi> ſpeaketh to this purpoſe, <hi>Nemo ſeparatim ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buiſſet Deos, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> novos ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> advenas:</hi> for God ſaith St. <hi>Bernard</hi> is not only <hi>vnus</hi> but <hi>vniſsimus:</hi> and as St. <hi>Gregory, Deus eſt intra omnia, extra omnia, ſupra omnia, infra omnia: ſuperior per po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam, inferior per ſuſtentationem, exterior per magnitudinem, interior per ſubtilitatem:</hi> creating all things, diſpoſing all things, ruling all things, directing all things; and therefore God only to be invocated as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> admoniſheth, <hi>whom haue I in heauen but thee,</hi> and in earth <hi>none in compariſon</hi> of thee. It is the <hi>Lords</hi> day, and to beſtow this <hi>pretious</hi> time impertinently, were but to gather ſticks vpon the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day. In this <hi>religious</hi> aſſembly, you may aske as hee did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a long Oration ſpent in the praiſe of <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, Quis vituperavit?</hi> who dare derogate from this great <hi>part of Gods ſeruice,</hi> which indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the whole <hi>worſhip of God?</hi> ſo Scripture expreſſeth it,<note place="margin">Gen 3.</note> 
               <hi>men began to call vpon the name of the Lord.</hi> I anſwer, wee know, and God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the Land mourneth for the <hi>apiſh Popiſh</hi> Idolatry of many who call vpon, not onely <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary ſaints,</hi> but vpon <hi>Statues,</hi> and <hi>pictures,</hi> and <hi>medalls,</hi> and <hi>Idolls,</hi> creeping to <hi>Croſſes,</hi> bowing to <hi>Images,</hi> like thoſe who turned the glory of the inviſible God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.20.</note> 
               <hi>into the ſimilitude of a Calfe that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15629:6"/>eateth hay.</hi> Giue me leaue therefore moſt <hi>briefly</hi> to put my <hi>Sithe</hi> into this <hi>Harueſt,</hi> not onely, to cut downe thoſe curſed <hi>tares,</hi> but alſo to gather ſome <hi>ſheaues</hi> for the preſent occaſion of this <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed</hi> Family, who when they ſee all helpe to be vaine, may the more <hi>earneſtly</hi> rely vpon the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> for their refuge: It is enough to <hi>ſtifle</hi> and <hi>ſtrangle</hi> this monſter of Idolatrous <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> that in all the <hi>Bible</hi> there is no one called vpon but <hi>God</hi> only; the <hi>godly</hi> in all ages neuer knew any <hi>other,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> hath no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of all the <hi>Scripture,</hi> but of damned <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues</hi> in hell, and let the <hi>wicked bee turned into hell, with all the people that forget God.</hi> The <hi>voice</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> is, <hi>Te Deum laudamus, Wee praiſe thee O God, wee acknowledge thee to be the Lord: All the earth doth worſhip thee: To thee all Angels cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud: To thee Cherubin and Seraphin, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally doe cry: The glorious company of the Apoſtles, the goodly fellowſhip of the Prophets, the noble army of Martyrs, the holy Church throughout the world, doth knowledge thee.</hi> Heare our Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> for all the reſt, as collecting this from all the reſt before him, and commending this practice vnto all that ſhall be after him, Thou Lord art the <hi>hope</hi> of all the ends of the <hi>Earth:</hi> Thou art <hi>God</hi> onely to be <hi>feared:</hi> Thou art God ouer all the Earth: Among the <hi>Gods</hi> none is like vnto thee: Thou art my <hi>rocke,</hi> my <hi>refuge,</hi> my <hi>ſhield,</hi> my <hi>buckler,</hi> my <hi>caſtle</hi> of defence, my <hi>deliuerance</hi> in whom I truſt. O <hi>loue</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> all yee that are his. And let mee draw you with a <hi>threefold</hi> cord of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15629:7"/>this loue, not eaſily to be broken, <hi>twiſted</hi> of the moſt pretious <hi>twines</hi> of his <hi>preſence,</hi> his <hi>omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> his <hi>beneficence.</hi> For his <hi>preſence,</hi> he is a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent help</hi> in trouble, hee filleth <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth:</hi> and as there is no <hi>place,</hi> where there is <hi>vacuitie,</hi> ſo there is no <hi>place,</hi> where there is not the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Deitie. Non eſt locus, vbi non eſt Deus:</hi> in the <hi>field</hi> with <hi>Iſaac,</hi> in the <hi>high-way</hi> with <hi>Iacob,</hi> in the <hi>pit</hi> with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> in the <hi>priſon</hi> with <hi>Micheas,</hi> in the <hi>dungeon</hi> with <hi>Ieremie,</hi> on the <hi>dung-hill</hi> with <hi>Iob,</hi> in the <hi>wilderneſſe</hi> with <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> on the <hi>Sea</hi> with <hi>Peter,</hi> in the <hi>Sea</hi> with <hi>Ionas,</hi> in the <hi>nethermoſt hell</hi> with <hi>Dauid, Thou haſt brought my ſoule from the nethermoſt hell. The Lord is nigh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all them that call vpon him,</hi> ſo nigh as that hee <hi>prepareth</hi> their hearts to call, <hi>hearkeneth</hi> to them <hi>when</hi> they <hi>call, inclineth</hi> himſelfe to <hi>receiue</hi> their <hi>call, boweth</hi> downe his care vnto their <hi>call;</hi> nay more, <hi>boweth</hi> the <hi>Heauens</hi> and commeth downe vpon their <hi>call;</hi> nay more, he commeth into them, <hi>ſtayeth</hi> with them, <hi>ſuppeth</hi> with them, <hi>lodgeth</hi> with them; nay yet <hi>more,</hi> will neuer bee <hi>abſent</hi> from them, but bee about their <hi>beds,</hi> about their <hi>pathes,</hi> about all their <hi>wayes,</hi> &amp; will for euer dwell in their <hi>hearts</hi> by faith. And as for his <hi>preſence,</hi> ſo for his <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> He is <hi>Creator adeſſe, Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uator in eſſe, Recreator in bene eſſe, Glorificator in optimo eſſe, He</hi> that meaſureth the <hi>Heauens</hi> with a <hi>ſpan,</hi> holdeth the <hi>Sea</hi> in his <hi>palme,</hi> weigheth the <hi>mountaines</hi> in <hi>ſcales,</hi> bindeth the <hi>earth</hi> in a <hi>girdle;</hi> Hee that out of the <hi>Stones</hi> in the <hi>ſtreet</hi> can <hi>raiſe children</hi> vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> open the <hi>windowes</hi> of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15629:7"/>
               <hi>heauen</hi> and <hi>raine plenty,</hi> can make <hi>fruitfull</hi> land barren, and water-ſprings of a dry land: He that <hi>bringeth downe</hi> the <hi>high</hi> tree, and <hi>exalteth</hi> the <hi>low</hi> tree, and <hi>dryeth</hi> vp the <hi>greene</hi> tree,<note place="margin">Eccle. 17.24.</note> and <hi>maketh</hi> the <hi>dry</hi> tree to <hi>flouriſh:</hi> he who with a word made <hi>all</hi> things, and with the ſame <hi>facilitie</hi> doth gouerne <hi>all</hi> things, and with the ſame <hi>abilitie</hi> ſhall deſtroy <hi>all</hi> things: hee who <hi>worketh</hi> all things, and is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>troubled;</hi> who <hi>worketh</hi> alwayes, and is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>diſquieted:</hi> who is in all <hi>places,</hi> and neuer <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth;</hi> who both <hi>filleth</hi> and <hi>incloſeth</hi> all things: <hi>He that is able to do exceeding abundantly, aboue all that we can aske or thinke, vnto him be glory in the Church by Chriſt Ieſus throghout all ages.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 3.20.</note> And as in his <hi>preſence</hi> and <hi>omnipotence,</hi> ſo in his <hi>beneficence:</hi> his <hi>grace,</hi> his <hi>good-will</hi> towards men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>tender</hi> mercies, the <hi>bowels</hi> of his mercies, the <hi>mercifull</hi> louing kindnes of the Lord, the <hi>height, the depth, the bredth, the length of the loue</hi> of God in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Deus meus, miſericordia mea:</hi> not <hi>miſericors Deus,</hi> but <hi>Deus meus, miſericordia mea:</hi> not, my mercifull God, or God of mercy; but, my God, my mercy. <hi>O nomen ſub quo nemini deſperandum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come hither then ſorrowfull Chriſtians,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> that feele an <hi>inviſible hand cutting downe our Royall Cedar,</hi> vnder whoſe gratious <hi>branches</hi> we thought to haue <hi>ſeene many good dayes;</hi> now yee ſee that they whom <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>called Gods,</hi> &amp; ſons of the moſt high, <hi>Quos homines, coeleſtibus aequat,</hi> hath taught them that leſſon, they muſt dye like men, <hi>Et Sceptra ligonibus aequat.</hi> O then truſt <hi>not in Princes. O bleſſed is the man that hath the God
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15629:8"/>of Iacob for his help:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 146.4.</note> whoſe <hi>hope is in the Lord his God.</hi> It was a good Speech in a bad King, who when the poore woman cryed out, <hi>Help me O my Lord the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 6.29.</note> hee anſwered, <hi>How ſhould I helpe thee when the Lord hath not helped mee.</hi> Alas, <hi>vaine is the help of man</hi> whatſoeuer he be.</p>
            <p>The firſt and laſt, higheſt and loweſt of all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> are all vanitie. Some <hi>few</hi> of them may bee <hi>Honourable</hi> becauſe <hi>Princes;</hi> but they are borne <hi>ſinfull,</hi> the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of <hi>men;</hi> and borne <hi>weake, there is no help in them;</hi> and borne <hi>mortall,</hi> their <hi>breath departeth;</hi> and borne <hi>corruptible,</hi> they <hi>returne to their earth:</hi> Truſt not then in Princes. And ſure, if the great <hi>Characters of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie,</hi> whoſe <hi>mortalitie</hi> this yeare hath made a large <hi>Commentary</hi> vpon thoſe words, ſerue not, The <hi>fatall Earth-quake</hi> vnder which this <hi>great Pile,</hi> and euery perſon therein, now laboureth in the bitter <hi>conflict</hi> betweene <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death</hi> of our <hi>Royall Maſter,</hi> (wherein <hi>O Lord ſend help vnto Iacob;</hi>) his <hi>ſad</hi> and <hi>heauy day,</hi> this <hi>diſaſtrous houre,</hi> might ſeale this <hi>leſſon</hi> to vs all our dayes, and lay it vp till the laſt <hi>houre</hi> of our <hi>life,</hi> Truſt not in Princes, <hi>Bleſſed is the man, who hath the God of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob for his help.</hi> Alas, how hath the <hi>witchcraft</hi> of <hi>Court</hi> ſo <hi>inticed</hi> and <hi>intangled</hi> many, that ſetling their <hi>eyes</hi> vpon <hi>ſublunary</hi> obiects: with the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, they <hi>forget God their helper,</hi> who ſtill <hi>haunt</hi> the <hi>Court,</hi> becauſe an <hi>vnquiet ſpirit haunteth them,</hi> whoſe <hi>ambitious wits</hi> being as high <hi>houſes</hi> vpon <hi>weake pillars,</hi> are eaſily <hi>blaſted</hi> and <hi>blowne downe,</hi> from <hi>aduancement</hi> or <hi>hope,</hi> from <hi>fruition,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15629:8"/>or <hi>poſsibility,</hi> though they thought to ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>preferment</hi> without <hi>Gods knowledge,</hi> beſides <hi>Gods will,</hi> and ſo they remaine <hi>bladders</hi> puft vp with the <hi>wind</hi> of <hi>falſe hope</hi> and <hi>ſelfe loue,</hi> confuſed <hi>heapes</hi> of <hi>enuy, pride,</hi> and <hi>emptineſſe:</hi> and why, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they called not <hi>vpon God: Happy</hi> is he, and <hi>bleſſed be God</hi> there be in <hi>Court</hi> many ſo <hi>happy,</hi> that know that <hi>the Court of heauen</hi> and earth, are not <hi>contrary</hi> but <hi>ſubordinate,</hi> and that the beſt <hi>Courtſhip</hi> ſprings from deuotion, when neither the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Court,</hi> nor <hi>grace</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> nor <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe</hi> of <hi>inferiours</hi> can make them <hi>looke aboue themſelues,</hi> or <hi>forget God</hi> or <hi>goodneſſe;</hi> to whom <hi>honeſty, reaſon</hi> and <hi>religion</hi> bee their <hi>chiefeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe,</hi> the <hi>Diall</hi> which they <hi>obſerue</hi> how to ſpend their <hi>time: Providebam Dominum,</hi> I did ſet the Lord alwaies before my eies: and <hi>ſo liue</hi> that though they know <hi>Princes fauours</hi> nor <hi>liues</hi> bee permanent, yet in the great <hi>ecclipſes</hi> of <hi>Court,</hi> ſuch as this our <hi>preſent diſtraction</hi> is, they <hi>remember</hi> there is a <hi>wide world</hi> beſides the <hi>Court,</hi> and a <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> aboue this <hi>world,</hi> where there is a <hi>God</hi> not ſubiect to <hi>change,</hi> but ready to <hi>heare,</hi> to <hi>helpe</hi> in a needfull <hi>time</hi> of trouble, as <hi>Dauids</hi> owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience here, <hi>Lord I beſeech thee ſend now proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> And ſo we are paſt our firſt ſtep.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I beſeech thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.</note> The <hi>perſon</hi> who it is by <hi>whom</hi> it is <hi>vttered.</hi> The Author of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> ſtory relateth, that when the <hi>Temple</hi> was to bee <hi>built,</hi> there was a <hi>ſtone</hi> often <hi>taken</hi> vp, but as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>refuſed</hi> by the <hi>workmen, ſometimes</hi> too <hi>bigge, ſomtimes</hi> too <hi>little,</hi> till at length it was placed as a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15629:9"/>conſpicuous <hi>corner</hi> ſtone aboue all the reſt.<note place="margin">Miſt. Eccl. in <hi>3.</hi> Reg.</note> 
               <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> paſſed through the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> ſubiect to many <hi>diſaſtrous influences,</hi> and yet remaineth ſtill the ſame, vntill the <hi>ſtorme</hi> of <hi>tyranny</hi> bee ouer-paſt: <hi>Enuy</hi> is like the <hi>Sun-beames,</hi> that beat more vpon a <hi>riſing ground,</hi> then vpon a <hi>levell;</hi> by many <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities</hi> hee came vnto that <hi>dignity</hi> hee had, his <hi>ſtanding</hi> was <hi>ſlippery,</hi> conſtrained to <hi>flie</hi> into the <hi>Rocke,</hi> to <hi>wander</hi> in the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> to <hi>lodge</hi> in a <hi>Caue,</hi> to <hi>beg</hi> his <hi>bread</hi> of <hi>Abimelech,</hi> to <hi>make</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a <hi>mad-man</hi> before <hi>Achiſh,</hi> to <hi>ſerue</hi> the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins</hi> his enemies; yet, all <hi>eyes</hi> are <hi>fixed</hi> vpon him, all <hi>tongues,</hi> all <hi>hearts, entertaining</hi> him the <hi>obiect</hi> of their <hi>diſcourſe</hi> and <hi>deſires;</hi> he being <hi>young</hi> and <hi>luſty</hi> as an <hi>Eagle, ſtrong</hi> as a <hi>Vnicorne, bold</hi> as a <hi>Lyon; running</hi> his <hi>race</hi> as a <hi>Gyant, flouriſhing</hi> as an <hi>Oliue-tree; eſtabliſhed</hi> as <hi>Mount Zion</hi> which cannot be remoued. I will not <hi>launch</hi> forth into the <hi>Ocean</hi> of <hi>Davids life,</hi> I will <hi>content</hi> my ſelfe to <hi>walk</hi> by ſome <hi>rivulets</hi> of the <hi>waters</hi> of <hi>comfort,</hi> which fall into the <hi>great Sea,</hi> wherein are things innumerable to be obſerued. In the <hi>Genealogie</hi> of Chriſt; among all the Kings there is not one ſtiled <hi>a King,</hi> but <hi>Dauid, Math.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Ieſſe</hi> begat <hi>Dauid</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> the <hi>King</hi> begate <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi> And of all the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iuda</hi> or <hi>Iſrael, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was the <hi>Patterne. Amaſiah</hi> did vprightly in the ſight of the Lord,<note place="margin">2 King. 14.</note> yet not like <hi>Dauid</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And <hi>Aſa</hi> did right in the ſight of the Lord as did <hi>Dauid</hi> his Father,<note place="margin">1 King. 15.</note> and ſo of the reſt; <hi>Dauid</hi> is ſo much renowned, as the <hi>principall</hi> and <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount Patterne</hi> of all the <hi>Royall</hi> line, that as in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15629:9"/>
               <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>bad Kings, Rehoboam</hi> did ill, and <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> worſe, and <hi>Omri</hi> worſe then he, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> worſe then all; ſo in the number of the good, though <hi>Salomon</hi> did well, <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> better then he, and <hi>Ioſias</hi> better then both, yet <hi>Dauid</hi> beſt of all, and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Diamond</hi> of the <hi>Diadem</hi> of all Kings, and of all <hi>other</hi> Kings this attribute in Scripture is giuen <hi>Dauid</hi> aboue all <hi>Kings,</hi> and before all <hi>Kings, Dauid the King.</hi> When <hi>Dauid</hi> was with <hi>Achiſh</hi> at <hi>Gath, Achiſh</hi> giueth this teſtimony vnto him, Thou art good in my ſight as an <hi>Angel of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 29.9.</note> when the woman of <hi>Tekoa,</hi> came with a <hi>pretence</hi> of getting a <hi>pardon</hi> for her baniſhed ſonne, ſhe vſeth the ſame termes to <hi>Dauid,</hi> As an <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14:17.</note> ſo is my Lord the <hi>King</hi> to diſcerne good and bad: when <hi>Dauid</hi> found the impoſture, that ſhee was <hi>Ioabs</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>Tekoite</hi> applies this againe to him, My Lord is wiſe according to the wiſdome of an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> of God,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.20.</note> to know all things that are in the earth: when <hi>Ziba</hi> had ſlandered <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> and <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> came being lame, ſomewhat late to anſwer for himſelfe to <hi>Dauid,</hi> My Lord the King, ſaith he, is an <hi>Angell of God:</hi> An at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute giuen him eſpecially <hi>among</hi> all the <hi>Kings, before</hi> all the <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>aboue</hi> all the Kings in Scripture, by enemies, ſtrangers, ſubiects, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, friends, good, bad, all,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.27.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> as an <hi>Angell of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Gregories</hi> obſeruation is true, <hi>Per incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. <hi>16.</hi> Hom. in Ezek.</note> 
               <hi>creuiſſe ſcientiam ſpiritualium Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum: Moſes</hi> partaked more diuine knowledge
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15629:10"/>then <hi>Abraham,</hi> the <hi>Prophets</hi> then <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> then the <hi>Prophets;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. Ep. <hi>6.</hi> ad Theodorum.</note> but of <hi>Dauid</hi> St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> noteth, <hi>vt in ordine regum, ſic in numero Prophetarum electum fuiſſe, Regum vero conſt at omnium optimum fuiſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Philaſter</hi> in the ſame kinde, <hi>Sicut ſanctis alijs diuerſam tribuit Chriſtus Dominus gratiam, it a majorem huic con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsit ſcientiam, dicente Domino, Dabo vobis ſancta fidelia Dauid. Aquinas</hi> proueth all the premiſes, <hi>quia Dauidi modus Prophetiae nobilior, videlicet per immediatam illuſtrationem intellectus:</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe explaineth the manner of his <hi>Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as the <hi>light</hi> of the morning when the <hi>Sunne</hi> ariſeth,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.4.</note> euen as a <hi>morning</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>clouds, as the tender graſſe ſpringing out of the earth, by cleere ſhining after raine:</hi> Summing vp Gods extraordinary graces in this kinde, <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.99.100.</note> 
               <hi>thou haſt giuen me more vnderſtanding then mine enemies, then my teachers, then my El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> So that <hi>Dauid</hi> a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and more then a <hi>Prophet,</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> &amp; the moſt worthy of al <hi>Kings,</hi> an <hi>Angell of God,</hi> and more then an <hi>Angell,</hi> as I ſhall now proue: for if the <hi>diſtinction</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> and their <hi>Hierarchy doe hold,</hi> and that of <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi> be true,<note place="margin">Dion. Arcop.</note> which the <hi>Ancients</hi> teach vs, <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin ordo Angelorum qui velociſſime pareant Deo,</hi> I ſay <hi>Dauid</hi> was as a <hi>ſwift wing'd Cherubin,</hi> of all <hi>others;</hi> through all the <hi>Scripture</hi> none ſo <hi>diuinely inſpired,</hi> with a <hi>hearty, holy, fiery</hi> zeale, <hi>flying</hi> vp into the <hi>ſpheare</hi> of <hi>diuine</hi> &amp; <hi>ſacred contemplation;</hi> none but hee that <hi>was</hi> the ſon of <hi>Dauid</hi> excelled <hi>Dauid</hi> in this <hi>kind.</hi> I know it is a ſtrange <hi>curioſity</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15629:10"/>to make a mans-ſelfe ſo <hi>skilfull</hi> in the orders of <hi>heauen,</hi> as to aduance <hi>Angell</hi> aboue <hi>Angell,</hi> and here it is little leſſe then an <hi>Impertinency;</hi> and I remember St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> dares not <hi>poſitiuely affirme</hi> it; but when I find of all other orders of <hi>Angells</hi> the <hi>Cherubins</hi> at the gate of <hi>Paradiſe, Cherubins</hi> ouer the <hi>Arke, Cherubins</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> the <hi>Oracle</hi> placed betweene the <hi>Cherubins,</hi> and the Chariot of Maieſtie drawne by <hi>Cherubins,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 18.11.</hi> Nyſſ. de Aſc. Domini, Daui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem maiorem eſſe Apoſtolis; &amp; Euangelica voce, ſublimio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> 
               <hi>He rode vpon the Cherubins and did flye,</hi> I then thinke, that <hi>as one ſtarre differeth from another ſtarre,</hi> ſo one <hi>Angell</hi> may differ from <hi>another Angell in glory;</hi> and if any <hi>Angell</hi> excell, the <hi>Cherubins</hi> doe; and if <hi>Dauid</hi> were as an <hi>Angell</hi> of God, becauſe he excelled <hi>other men,</hi> I dare ſay by his <hi>deuotion</hi> wherein he <hi>excelled,</hi> he was a glorious <hi>Cherubin:</hi> deuotion was his daily <hi>bread,</hi> his <hi>meat,</hi> his <hi>drinke,</hi> his diuine and deareſt <hi>exerciſe;</hi> I giue my ſelfe, ſaith he, vnto <hi>Prayer:</hi> doth <hi>dedicate</hi> &amp; <hi>conſecrate</hi> his <hi>time</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtudie</hi> and <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>endeauor,</hi> his <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>tongue,</hi> and <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> and <hi>ſoule</hi> vnto this bleſſed duty and <hi>ſeruice,</hi> to this diuine and heauenly <hi>exerciſe, I giue my ſelfe vnto Praeyer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord hath choſe vnto himſelfe the man that is godly;</hi> that is, ſaith the <hi>Chalde</hi> Paraphraſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> the man that can pray. The Lord hath magnifyed, ſo St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> readeth <hi>magnificavit,</hi> or as <hi>Ierome, mirificauit.</hi> Surely bleſſed is that man that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath endowed with the <hi>leaſt meaſure</hi> of his <hi>ſpirit,</hi> with one <hi>dramme</hi> of <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> with one <hi>ſparke</hi> of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> one <hi>drop</hi> of <hi>heauenly dew,</hi> one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15629:11"/>
               <hi>mite</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> one <hi>grain</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> one <hi>Iota</hi> of <hi>firme obedience;</hi> but when the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſhowred ſo <hi>plentifull a dew</hi> vpon his <hi>inheritance,</hi> and ſo vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly <hi>magnified</hi> and <hi>multiplied</hi> all theſe <hi>bleſsings</hi> vpon a man, then wee may ſay as it was of <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dochai, Thus ſhall it be done vnto the man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſt. 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>whom the King of heauen delighteth to honour;</hi> and ſuch honour haue all his <hi>Saints;</hi> but aboue all <hi>Dauid</hi> had this <hi>honour,</hi> which being <hi>diſtilled</hi> and <hi>infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> on him, hee <hi>deriueth</hi> to others, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his Commandement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 112.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>his ſeed ſhall be great vpon earth, his generation ſhall bee bleſſed, wealth and riches ſhall be in his houſe, and his righteouſneſse ſhall endure for euer.</hi> To cloſe vp my obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Dauids</hi> perſon, he was not only <hi>Gods</hi> friend as his <hi>name</hi> importeth, but <hi>Gods fauorite,</hi> like the <hi>Diſciple</hi> whom <hi>Ieſus</hi> loued, and therefore moſt <hi>familiar</hi> in <hi>Gods boſome,</hi> and chiefe of his <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>priuy Councell.</hi> Six times we read of <hi>Dauids</hi> familiar acceſſe, to <hi>conſult God</hi> himſelfe; <hi>Dauid</hi> enquired of the Lord,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 23 2.</note> Shall I goe ſmite the <hi>Philiſtius. Dauid</hi> againe enquired of the <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 23.4.</note> Shall I goe downe to <hi>Keilah. Dauid</hi> yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine enquired of the Lord, whether hee ſhould purſue the troope that had ſackt <hi>Ziglag.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 30.8.</note> When he newly came to the <hi>Crowne; Dauid</hi> enquired of the Lord,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2:1.</note> Shall I goe into any of the Cities of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah:</hi> when all the Tribes had annointed him King in <hi>Hebron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.19.</note> and the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> came againſt him, <hi>Dauid</hi> enquired of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> came vpon <hi>Iſrael</hi> for <hi>Sauls</hi> bloody act in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15629:11"/>ſlaying the <hi>Gibeonites. Dauid</hi> enquired of the Lord; or, as in the <hi>Originall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.1.</note> Sought the fauor of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Imitation</hi> whereof will bleſſe your <hi>graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Highneſſe; for as <hi>Gregory</hi> propoſeth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> of all others, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite <hi>Rulers</hi> to enter into the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult</hi> with God; not to come to their <hi>Counſell-Table,</hi> before they <hi>aske counſell,</hi> and pray for <hi>counſell</hi> from God; and euen <hi>Pliny</hi> giueth a reaſon hereof, <hi>Nihilrecte, nihil prudenter, nihil prouidenter, homines ſine Deorum immortalium ope, conſilio, honore, auſpicari:</hi> Let it not bee <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable,</hi> that I preſſe this at <hi>this inſtant,</hi> now your <hi>Royall</hi> Father lyeth vpon the <hi>Altar</hi> of his Death-bed, for the <hi>ſacrificing</hi> of his <hi>bleſſed Soule</hi> to his <hi>Redeemer, The Lord helpe him in this Day of trouble, the name of the God of Iacob defend him.</hi> I will not ſay that <hi>trouble is hard at hand;</hi> and yet <hi>Corona gemmarum,</hi> is but <hi>Corona ſpina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> but a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>weighty Charge,</hi> is ready to fall vpon your <hi>Princely ſhoulders,</hi> a great <hi>doore</hi> is opening to your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> and there bee many <hi>Aduerſaries:</hi> vpon whom are all the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>eyes,</hi> I ſay, not of theſe <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> but of the <hi>Chriſtian World, ſet,</hi> but vpon your <hi>Highneſse?</hi> and as <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſpake, <hi>who knoweth whether you are come to the Kingdome for ſuch a time as this is?</hi> to be the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſter 4.14.</note> and enuy of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> World; for, ſince the <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> went downe into <hi>Egypt, vt qui populus perſecutor fuit populi primogeniti, fieret
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15629:12"/>cuſtos filii Primogeniti,</hi> neuer was any <hi>Prince</hi> ſo deliuered out of the hands of his <hi>Enemies,</hi> that hee might ſerue the <hi>Lord</hi> without <hi>feare;</hi> neuer any <hi>Prince</hi> brought back from the <hi>imminent, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, emergent</hi> Iawes of death, as your <hi>Gracious Perſon:</hi> O, let it neuer bee <hi>vnſauory</hi> to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that <hi>miraculous ſafety</hi> of your <hi>Highneſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne;</hi> wherein the right hand <hi>of the Lord</hi> had the preheminence,<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.</note> the <hi>right hand of the Lord brought mighty things to paſſe.</hi> O, let it bee your <hi>Religious care,</hi> that euer your <hi>Soule</hi> may bee <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied</hi> with the <hi>bleſsings</hi> of <hi>good</hi> things by <hi>prayer,</hi> that your <hi>Sacred Perſon</hi> may bee, as <hi>euer hitherto you haue beene,</hi> a bleſſed <hi>Patterne</hi> of this holy <hi>practice;</hi> for <hi>ſuch</hi> as your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> ſhall <hi>appeare</hi> to bee by <hi>example</hi> and <hi>proucation,</hi> ſuch will your <hi>Seruants</hi> bee by <hi>imitation:</hi> For, as all in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders</hi> time, did affect <hi>Chiualry,</hi> becauſe hee was a <hi>Souldier;</hi> and <hi>Poetry</hi> in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> time, becauſe hee loued <hi>Poets;</hi> and <hi>Muſicke</hi> in <hi>Nero's</hi> time, becauſe hee was a <hi>Muſitian;</hi> and <hi>Fencing</hi> in <hi>Commodus</hi> time, becauſe hee delighted in <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers:</hi> ſo all were forward in <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi> time, becauſe hee loued <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> of whom as the <hi>powerfull</hi> examples of other ages in <hi>Hercules</hi> fortitude,<note place="margin">Guevar. Epiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Antonius Pius</hi> his care of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his learning, <hi>Cato</hi> his Seuerity, <hi>Scipio</hi> his Continency, and <hi>Laelius</hi> his Amity, were Preſidents to all ſucceeding Ages; ſo was <hi>Conſtantine</hi> of deuout Piety: who, the better to inſtruct his People in <hi>Deuotion,</hi> by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15629:12"/>ordained that his <hi>Image,</hi> which we know Princes doe vſe to coyne vpon their money, ſhould bee <hi>ſtamp'd</hi> with the reſemblance of him praying: And to ſay no more herein,<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſtan. C. <hi>15.</hi> Cyp. de coena Dom.</note> I cloſe this with <hi>Cyprian, Quoties in conſpectu Domini video aliquem ſuſpirantem, toties Spiritum ſanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non dubito inſpirantem:</hi> As often as I ſee any one in <hi>Gods</hi> fight <hi>ſighing</hi> out <hi>prayers;</hi> ſo often I doubt not <hi>God</hi> is preſent, <hi>breathing</hi> his <hi>Spirit</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a holy <hi>ſuppliant. Diuinity</hi> buildeth vpon this, <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> doth require it, <hi>neceſsity</hi> doth <hi>enforce</hi> it, and no <hi>faithfull</hi> man maketh <hi>doubt</hi> of it; and hee that ſhall bee <hi>frequent</hi> in it, ſhall be ſure to finde <hi>fauour</hi> of the <hi>Almightie:</hi> O, did they conſider this that <hi>dote</hi> vpon <hi>Courtly</hi> fauour, the <hi>Courts diety, Ambitions Darling:</hi> vpon <hi>fauour</hi> that <hi>flower, vapour, meteor; palea, feſtuca, vmbra, pluma, ſpuma;</hi> that <hi>ſhadow,</hi> that <hi>duſt,</hi> that <hi>mote,</hi> that <hi>feather,</hi> that <hi>froth:</hi> vpon <hi>fauour</hi> that <hi>ebbeth</hi> as the <hi>Sea, paſſeth</hi> as a <hi>winde,</hi> and <hi>droppeth</hi> downe as the <hi>leaues</hi> in the <hi>fall,</hi> they would learne <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> leſſon, to ſeeke <hi>fauour</hi> and <hi>familiarity</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> for <hi>that ſhall bring a man peace at the laſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note> &amp; would make this their dayly ſuit, as <hi>Dauid,</hi> a King, being <hi>Maſter of Requeſts</hi> for himſelfe, here doth, <hi>I beſeech thee O Lord, O Lord I beſeech thee:</hi> and ſo I haue done with the ſecond ſtep.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I beſeech thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">3.</note> the manner <hi>how</hi> hee prayeth. <hi>Deuotion</hi> delayed or lingred, is ſoone <hi>quenched,</hi> but when <hi>heated,</hi> and <hi>haſtened,</hi> when the <hi>paſsions</hi> are <hi>liuely</hi> and <hi>ſtrong,</hi> when an <hi>earneſt, Zealous, impetuous</hi> Petition is offered to God, not drawn
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15629:13"/>from the <hi>lips</hi> or <hi>lungs,</hi> but from the <hi>inwards</hi> of a <hi>contrite, confident</hi> Soule, it neuer wanteth ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; for not only the <hi>Body</hi> but the <hi>Soule</hi> hath a <hi>mouth,</hi> and <hi>language;</hi> and as the <hi>heart</hi> giueth <hi>aſpiration</hi> to the <hi>arteries,</hi> ſo doth the <hi>conſcience</hi> to the <hi>affections;</hi> and as we <hi>breathe</hi> in the <hi>ayre,</hi> ſo <hi>grace</hi> is <hi>breathed</hi> into vs from <hi>Heauen;</hi> the <hi>motions</hi> of <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> are the <hi>lungs, knowledge</hi> and <hi>deuotion</hi> are as the <hi>lips, faith</hi> as the <hi>tongue, zeale</hi> as a <hi>ſtring</hi> that paſſeth from the <hi>heart</hi> vnto the <hi>tongue; Prayer</hi> is the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the <hi>holy</hi> Tongue; for ſhee was bred in the <hi>holy</hi> Land, and the <hi>elegance</hi> of this Tongue, is the <hi>elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> of importunity.<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>Quam grata apud Deum importunitas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> how gracious and gratefull is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity in the eares of God? <hi>Non importunus ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> impudens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de verb. Apoſt.</note> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> it is not a <hi>ſawcy</hi> or a <hi>ſhameleſſe</hi> part in thee to aske any thing of God with great <hi>importunity,</hi> hee bids thee <hi>aske,</hi> and <hi>ſeeke,</hi> and <hi>knock,</hi> and <hi>knocke</hi> not only til he <hi>heare,</hi> but till hee <hi>anſwer,</hi> and <hi>open,</hi> and <hi>grant</hi> thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. <hi>Dauid</hi> hath a double <hi>ſupplication,</hi> it is like the <hi>former</hi> and the <hi>latter</hi> raine, the <hi>ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> noteth an <hi>vnremoueable</hi> and conſtant <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> to the ſuit hee <hi>deſireth;</hi> mans <hi>impatience</hi> in prayer can neuer <hi>offend</hi> Gods <hi>patience,</hi> the Muſicke of <hi>Angels</hi> doth not more <hi>delight</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> then the <hi>redoubled obſecrations</hi> of his <hi>Seruants,</hi> wherby he doth <hi>ſuſpend</hi> their <hi>deſires</hi> in expectation, &amp; extend them by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their earneſt <hi>importunity:</hi> Note only the <hi>Parables</hi> of a <hi>friend</hi> called vp at <hi>mid-night,</hi> the moſt <hi>vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15629:13"/>and <hi>deadeſt time,</hi> wherein any would bee loth to be <hi>troubled,</hi> the <hi>doores</hi> ſhut, the <hi>children</hi> aſleep, the <hi>ſable mantle</hi> of the <hi>ſilent night,</hi> couering all the <hi>World;</hi> yet vpon <hi>importunity</hi> the <hi>friend</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth at <hi>midnight, anſwereth, openeth, granteth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note> the requeſt, <hi>tendreth</hi> and <hi>giueth,</hi> becauſe of the importunity; ſo alſo that <hi>Parable</hi> of the <hi>vniuſt Iudge,</hi> that cared neither for <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>man;</hi> yet becauſe of the <hi>conſtant, continuall</hi> Solicitation of the <hi>poore woman,</hi> he <hi>heard</hi> her, and <hi>granted</hi> her ſuit: wee cannot hold a <hi>meaner opinion</hi> of God, then of a <hi>common vulgar Friend,</hi> (which were too baſe to conceiue) or a more <hi>vnrighteous</hi> iudgement of him, then of the moſt <hi>vnrighteous Iudge,</hi> (then which,<note place="margin">Aqu. Cat. Aug.</note> what can bee thought more blaſphemous) they both were <hi>woone, non amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, non iuſtitia compulſi, ſed taedio. Famous</hi> is the <hi>importunity</hi> of the poore woman of <hi>Canaan, miſerere fili Dauid.</hi> 1. She <hi>cryeth,</hi> and <hi>calleth,</hi> and <hi>followeth:</hi> our <hi>Sauiour</hi> vouchſafeth not an <hi>anſwer,</hi> not a <hi>word,</hi> not a <hi>looke,</hi> yet ſhee <hi>ſurceaſeth</hi> not, but <hi>calleth</hi> and <hi>cryeth</hi> out ſtill. 2. The <hi>Diſciples</hi> her <hi>back-frinds,</hi> they would haue her ſent <hi>backe,</hi> Send her away, ſhe <hi>cryeth after vs,</hi> and yet ſhee is not <hi>retarded,</hi> but <hi>continueth</hi> her calling. 3. Our Sauiour <hi>anſwereth</hi> her, and <hi>reiecteth</hi> her, as not <hi>capable</hi> of any good from <hi>him, I am not ſent but to the loſt ſheepe of Iſrael:</hi> ſhee a <hi>Canaanite,</hi> yet neither <hi>Diſciples</hi> nor <hi>Maſter</hi> can <hi>beat</hi> backe her Faith, ſhee <hi>followeth,</hi> and <hi>falleth downe,</hi> and <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippeth,</hi> and <hi>cryeth</hi> Lord helpe me. 4. Our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour replieth</hi> in the moſt bitter <hi>Phraſe</hi> that euer
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15629:14"/>hee vſed to any poore <hi>Suiter,</hi> It is not meete to take the <hi>childrens bread and to giue it to dogs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> The <hi>daughter</hi> poſſeſſed with a <hi>Deuill,</hi> the mother ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a <hi>dog,</hi> and holy things not to be <hi>giuen</hi> to dogs, this had bin <hi>enough</hi> to haue <hi>blaſted</hi> her <hi>hope,</hi> and <hi>rooted</hi> vp her <hi>faith,</hi> and haue confounded her <hi>confidence,</hi> and <hi>wounded</hi> her <hi>diſtreſſed ſoule,</hi> and <hi>ſilenced</hi> her <hi>importunity;</hi> yet behold, ſhe that had all theſe <hi>diſcouragements,</hi> replieth, and by her <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply crowneth</hi> her <hi>confidence</hi> with a bleſſed <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, Truth Lord, but the dogs eate of the crummes that fall from their Maſters table. She</hi> wrought a <hi>miracle</hi> vpon her <hi>Sauiour,</hi> made the <hi>deafe</hi> eares to <hi>heare,</hi> and the <hi>dumbe</hi> tongue to ſpeake: to <hi>tongue</hi> and <hi>eares,</hi> ſhee cryed as <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>eyes</hi> of the blind, <hi>Ephata,</hi> bee opened, heare and <hi>anſwer</hi> my petition, and grant my requeſt. O how well <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> is the Lord with the <hi>importunity</hi> of his <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants</hi> when they cry <hi>day</hi> and <hi>night,</hi> and double their <hi>ingeminated obſecrations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Looke vpon bleſſed <hi>Hezekias</hi> his manner of <hi>Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 37.17.</note> Encline thine eares <hi>O Lord</hi> and <hi>heare,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen thine <hi>eyes</hi> O Lord and <hi>ſee,</hi> &amp; <hi>heare;</hi> and when he lay vpon his <hi>death-bed</hi> chattering like a ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, mourning like a <hi>Doue,</hi> I am depriued of the <hi>reſidue of my yeares,</hi> I ſaid I ſhall not ſee <hi>the Lord, euen the Lord in the Land of the liuing:</hi> hee knew that no balme in <hi>Gilead,</hi> no <hi>vnguent</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries,</hi> no <hi>skill</hi> of <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> no <hi>fruits</hi> of the <hi>fields,</hi> no <hi>flowers</hi> of the <hi>garden,</hi> no <hi>mineralls</hi> of the <hi>ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 38.</note> could giue the leaſt allay vnto his <hi>ſicke</hi> and <hi>ſorrowfull</hi> ſoule, but onely the <hi>Lord,</hi> whom
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15629:14"/>therefore hee remembreth, and ſixe <hi>times in his Prayer</hi> repeateth that ſacred name of the <hi>Lord.</hi> It is obſerued that God himſelfe doth ſeeme to be pleaſed to vſe often an <hi>ingemination</hi> of the <hi>names</hi> of thoſe he beſt <hi>loued,</hi> in <hi>Scripture;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.11. Exod. 3.4. 1 Sam 3.10.</note> as when he called <hi>Abraham, Abraham, Moſes, Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Samuel, Samuel:</hi> &amp; in a <hi>like manner</hi> we ought to be well <hi>pleaſed</hi> and much <hi>delighted</hi> in the <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> remembrance and inuocation of his <hi>name.</hi> And ſure when the <hi>hart</hi> is full of God, the <hi>tongue</hi> will not refraine to <hi>talke of him,</hi> they that rarely <hi>thinke on God,</hi> ſhew how <hi>miſerable</hi> their eſtate of <hi>grace</hi> is. If the <hi>Lord</hi> be not in our <hi>hearts</hi> wee are <hi>godleſſe;</hi> if in our <hi>hearts</hi> without <hi>ioy,</hi> we are <hi>hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe:</hi> If wee <hi>reioyce in him,</hi> and <hi>ſpeake</hi> not of <hi>him,</hi> we are <hi>ſhamefully thankleſſe;</hi> If he be in our <hi>harts</hi> in our <hi>tongues,</hi> in our <hi>ioy, coldly</hi> and <hi>perfunctorily,</hi> we are <hi>negligently faithleſſe:</hi> and therefore as wee muſt <hi>thinke</hi> on the Lord <hi>alwayes,</hi> ſo <hi>ſpeake</hi> on <hi>him often,</hi> and when we pray to him, doe it <hi>earneſtly,</hi> and <hi>zealouſly;</hi> in <hi>faith</hi> without <hi>wauering,</hi> in <hi>confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> without <hi>doubting,</hi> in <hi>perſeuerance</hi> without <hi>deſiſting,</hi> crying out as <hi>Ionas</hi> Mariners,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ion.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee O Lord, wee beeſeech thee;</hi> or as <hi>Dauid</hi> here, <hi>I beſeech thee O Lord, O Lord I beſeech thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To land this point, <hi>reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber</hi> that the <hi>Church</hi> hath appointed vs to <hi>pray,</hi> in al <hi>time</hi> of our <hi>tribulation,</hi> in all <hi>time</hi> of our <hi>wealth,</hi> &amp; in the houre of <hi>death.</hi> In all time of our <hi>tribulation</hi> we are <hi>ready</hi> to <hi>pray,</hi> but in the time of our <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>proſperity</hi> we are <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to <hi>deuotion;</hi> yet in the time of thy <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>health</hi> remember <hi>tribulation,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15629:15"/>in the daies of thy <hi>peace,</hi> thy <hi>viſitation;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy <hi>houre</hi> of death: for when <hi>ryot</hi> hath beene <hi>maſter of miſ-rule,</hi> and turned <hi>ſobriety</hi> the <hi>good ſteward</hi> out of doore, and <hi>Intemperance</hi> an <hi>vnbidden gueſt,</hi> hath <hi>got</hi> in, and <hi>defiled</hi> all the <hi>roomes</hi> of thy <hi>body; Nature</hi> like a <hi>good-huſwife</hi> would willingly <hi>cleanſe the houſe,</hi> and <hi>deſires</hi> the <hi>helpe</hi> of <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> as a <hi>Scauinger,</hi> to <hi>make cleane</hi> the <hi>roomes;</hi> but alas, <hi>ſhe findeth</hi> that <hi>ſinne</hi> lyeth like a <hi>dog</hi> at the <hi>doore,</hi> and <hi>death</hi> the <hi>cruell Serjeant threatens</hi> to <hi>ſerue</hi> an <hi>extent</hi> vpon the whole <hi>houſe,</hi> there is no ſuch <hi>meanes</hi> to quit thee of thy <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe</hi> and of thy <hi>direfull enemy</hi> as <hi>prayer:</hi> it is <hi>Dauids Antidote,</hi> but thou muſt take it <hi>faſting,</hi> and bee ſure to take it <hi>warme,</hi> it muſt bee <hi>feruent prayer;</hi> and take it not onely <hi>morning</hi> and <hi>euening,</hi> but take it as a <hi>continuall</hi> Cordiall, and cry <hi>mightily, Haue mercy, haue mercy, Spare me O Lord, ſpare me O Lord, I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to heare me.</hi> And ſo being <hi>ſtedfaſt,</hi> and <hi>vnmoueable,</hi> and <hi>alwayes abounding</hi> in this <hi>worke</hi> of the Lord, thou ſhalt finde that thy <hi>labour</hi> ſhall not be in vaine in the Lord. And ſo I haue <hi>ended</hi> my third <hi>ſtep,</hi> the manner <hi>how</hi> hee earneſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored: I will <hi>mend</hi> my pace, for it is the <hi>day of our Royall Iacobs wreſtling,</hi> and I feare, as <hi>Eliſha heard</hi> the ſound of <hi>Iehorams feet</hi> following the <hi>bloody meſſenger</hi> ſent to take away his life, ſo my <hi>heart</hi> trembleth to thinke it, and my <hi>cares</hi> tingle to <hi>heare,</hi> the <hi>heauie</hi> and ſad <hi>approach</hi> of <hi>pale Death</hi> entring into this <hi>Kingly Palace.</hi> O that we could with <hi>Eliſha</hi> looke heedfully now this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15629:15"/>
               <hi>meſſenger,</hi> this <hi>murtherer</hi> commeth,<note place="margin">2. Kings 6.32.</note> and that we could by our <hi>prayers</hi> ſhut the <hi>doore,</hi> and hold him <hi>faſt</hi> at the <hi>doore,</hi> and this <hi>prayer</hi> might <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, O Lord I beſeech thee ſaue now, O Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee ſend now proſperity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Send Proſperity: Praeuentions</hi> of <hi>Paliticians, preſumptions</hi> of the <hi>fooliſh, circumſpection</hi> of the <hi>wiſe, circumuention</hi> of the <hi>wits,</hi> are all <hi>Arts Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>webs,</hi> and <hi>experience paper Caſtles,</hi> the <hi>Silk-worms</hi> worke, and the <hi>fooles</hi> wonder, <hi>Proſperity</hi> is only the gift of the <hi>father</hi> of lights. The old <hi>Speech</hi> is, that <hi>wiſe men</hi> cauſe <hi>proſperous times:</hi> But alas, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie</hi> trippeth vp ſacred <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> for <hi>Policie</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome</hi> differ as much as <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha;</hi> and <hi>Policie</hi> is often as offenſiue to true <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> as <hi>Hagar</hi> to <hi>Sarah,</hi> and ſometimes as <hi>iniurious,</hi> as <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer was to <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Copper-ſmith</hi> to <hi>Paul. Laertius</hi> tels vs of certaine young men of <hi>Ionia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diog. Laer. de vit. Philoſ.</note> ſtanding on the <hi>ſhore,</hi> agreed with certaine <hi>Fiſher-men</hi> for the next <hi>draught,</hi> in which there being a <hi>rich</hi> and precious peece of <hi>Plate,</hi> they not agreeing whoſe by <hi>right</hi> it was, they went to conſult the <hi>Oracle;</hi> the <hi>Oracle</hi> enioyned them to ſend it to the <hi>wiſeſt man</hi> aliue, they thereupon ſent it to <hi>Thales,</hi> hee diſclaimed it, and ſent it to <hi>another,</hi> who alſo <hi>refuſed</hi> it, till hauing paſſed through <hi>many,</hi> who all denyed that <hi>attribute</hi> of the <hi>wiſeſt,</hi> to belong to <hi>them,</hi> at length they bring it to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and hee wiſhed them to ſend it to the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> at <hi>Delphos,</hi> and to preſent it to <hi>God,</hi> as being the moſt wife, according to that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> To
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15629:16"/>God <hi>only-wiſe.</hi> And ſurely, as <hi>God</hi> is called by the name of <hi>Wiſedome;</hi> ſo men come neere to God in <hi>nothing</hi> more then the <hi>ſtudy</hi> of <hi>Wiſedome;</hi> wherein all the <hi>Politicians</hi> of the World out of their <hi>Chymical limbiques,</hi> with al their <hi>extraction,</hi> can neuer doe <hi>good,</hi> vnleſſe their <hi>wiſedome</hi> bee ſeaſoned from aboue. It is <hi>God</hi> only that can both make <hi>wiſe men</hi> and <hi>proſperous times:</hi> and therefore our Prophet directeth his <hi>Prayer</hi> aright, <hi>O Lord ſend proſperity:</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> readeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> which was <hi>ſung</hi> before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is now <hi>ſung</hi> before <hi>Dauid:</hi> a word that is <hi>variouſly</hi> interpreted by the <hi>Ancients</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne,</hi> ſignifying, ſaith <hi>Euthymius,</hi> a <hi>Hymne</hi> or <hi>Song:</hi> or the <hi>branches</hi> of <hi>Oliues</hi> and <hi>Palmes,</hi> born before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Caninius:</hi> or the redemption of the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> or <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> as <hi>Chryſoſtome:</hi> it is <hi>interiectio gaudentis, &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrantis,</hi> as <hi>Auſtine:</hi> and as much as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>proceſſus, ſucceſſus,</hi> a <hi>voyce</hi> and <hi>vote</hi> of <hi>happy ſucceſſe.</hi> It is like that in the firſt Pſalme, <hi>Omnia quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> faciet proſperabuntur.</hi> All the foure <hi>Euangeliſts</hi> mention this <hi>Iubilation</hi> at the <hi>comming of our Sauiour</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> wherein <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>followers,</hi> and <hi>young,</hi> and <hi>old, men, women,</hi> and <hi>children</hi> bare a part. It is a frequent <hi>acclamation</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> God ſaue the King, not onely to <hi>Salomon</hi> the <hi>good,</hi> but to <hi>Saul</hi> the <hi>bad,</hi> and to <hi>Adonijah</hi> the <hi>Vſurper;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 1.39. 1 Sam. 10.24. 1 Kin. 1.25.</note> but <hi>Hoſanna</hi> onely ſung to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and to the <hi>Soune</hi> of <hi>Dauid, Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> I will not ſtriue to enter into the meaning or <hi>myſtery</hi> of this <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Iubilation;</hi> Alas, it is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15629:16"/>a word <hi>out of ſeaſon,</hi> and <hi>all our Inſtruments are out of tune,</hi> and wee are <hi>here as they that ſate weeping at the waters of Babylon,</hi> wee haue <hi>hang'd</hi> vp our <hi>harps</hi> vpon the <hi>willowes;</hi> this is not a <hi>time</hi> to ſing the ſongs of <hi>Sion,</hi> none may require this <hi>ſong</hi> of vs in our heauineſſe. <hi>Lorinus</hi> obſerueth,<note place="margin">Lor. in Pſ. <hi>116.</hi>
               </note> that of all other the <hi>Euangeliſts,</hi> S. <hi>Luke</hi> omitteth this word <hi>Hoſanna, Qui Graeci ſermonis eruditiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, videns ſe proprietatem ſermonis transferre non poſſe, melius arbitratus eſt tacere, quam id ponere quod legenti faceret quaeſtionem,</hi> and therefore I will content my ſelfe as it is here <hi>rendred, Lord ſend proſperity.</hi> It was an vſuall forme of <hi>Morning Prayer</hi> among the <hi>Iewes, Proſper vs O Lord, O Lord ſend vs now proſperity; proſper thou the worke of our hands vnto vs, O proſper thou our handy worke.</hi> It was the <hi>Religious care</hi> of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seruant, when being ſent to <hi>ſolicite</hi> for a <hi>Wife</hi> for <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and knowing that it was not to bee <hi>enterpriſed vnaduiſedly</hi> or <hi>lightly,</hi> hee <hi>prayed</hi> in his <hi>Iourney:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 24.12.21.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord God I beſeech thee ſend mee good ſpeed, or proſperity, this day.</hi> And when <hi>hee</hi> came vnto the <hi>Well,</hi> he ſtood <hi>wauering</hi> in <hi>contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation,</hi> whether the Lord <hi>had made his iourney proſperous or not;</hi> and when the Match was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, <hi>Hinder me not</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>ſeeing the Lord hath proſpered my way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Proſperity is not the <hi>faire Gale</hi> of <hi>temporall carnall ſecurity, puffing</hi> vp the <hi>ſuperſtitious ſailes</hi> of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>ambition.</hi> If thou hadſt,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> the <hi>wiſe dome</hi> of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the <hi>beauty</hi> of <hi>Abſolon,</hi> the <hi>long life</hi> of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15629:17"/>
               <hi>Methuſhelah,</hi> the <hi>riches</hi> of <hi>Diues,</hi> the <hi>dyet</hi> of the <hi>Glutton,</hi> who fared <hi>deliciouſly</hi> euery day. <hi>Quid proſunt haec, cum caro datur vermibus, Anima Daemonibus?</hi> Looke vpon <hi>Dauids</hi> two <hi>trees,</hi> the <hi>Bay-tree,</hi> and the <hi>Oliue-tree,</hi> and then <hi>obſerue</hi> the difference between <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ſeeming</hi> proſperity. <hi>I haue ſeene the wicked in great power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.36.</note> 
               <hi>and ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding like a greene Bay-tree: yet hee paſſed away &amp; loe he was not: I ſought him, but hee could not bee found.</hi> Here is that <hi>inticing trap, ſugred poyſon, venomous pill, ſtupifying perfume,</hi> that <hi>golden net,</hi> and <hi>goodly, Babyloniſh garment,</hi> like that <hi>Fruit</hi> which our firſt <hi>Parents</hi> taſted:<note place="margin">Pro. 1.31.</note> 
               <hi>Pulcher in viſu, mollis in tactie, dulcis in guſtu, mortifer in effectu.</hi> The proſperity of <hi>fooles ſhall deſtroy them,</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsing them with irreligious <hi>prophaneſſe,</hi> and ſo <hi>infatuating</hi> them, that their <hi>hearts</hi> are as <hi>dead peeces</hi> of <hi>fleſh,</hi> without <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>feare,</hi> or <hi>loue,</hi> or <hi>care,</hi> or <hi>paine,</hi> from the <hi>deafe ſtrokes</hi> of a <hi>reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging conſcience.</hi> This drew that ſtrange <hi>expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> from <hi>Ieremy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 12.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Righteous art thou O Lord, when I plead with thee; yet let me talke with thee of thy Iudgements: Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper? wherefore are they happy that deale trecherouſly? Thou haſt planted them, and they haue taken root, and grow and bring forth; thou art neere in their mouth, but far from their reynes: pull them out like ſheepe for the ſlaughter, &amp; prepare them for the day of ſlaughter.</hi> But now, if you pleaſe, looke vpon <hi>Dauids Oliue-tree,</hi> or rather <hi>Dauid</hi> as an <hi>Oliue-tree;</hi> I am like a greene <hi>Oliue-tree</hi> in the houſe of my God <hi>for euer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 52.9.</note> not as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15629:17"/>
               <hi>Nebuchadonozors</hi> tree, hewed downe; or as the wicked mans <hi>Bay</hi> tree, fel'd downe; or as <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> tree, cut downe and <hi>caſt into the fire:</hi> but the <hi>greene, pleaſant, fragrant, flouriſhing, Oliue-tree:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue came to him with an <hi>Oliue</hi> branch, in her mouth, and that <hi>branch</hi> was the Embleme of a <hi>bleſsing:</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the reaſon, why an <hi>Oliue branch;</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe the <hi>leaues</hi> thereof are moſt <hi>beautifull,</hi> but that they <hi>liue</hi> vnder <hi>water,</hi> as it is certaine the <hi>Oliue-tree</hi> continued in the great <hi>Catacliſme</hi> and <hi>Inundation</hi> of <hi>Waters:</hi> And indeed, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> of all <hi>trees,</hi> maketh eſpeciall menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Oliue-tree,</hi> that whereas <hi>Iob</hi> compares the <hi>Rich</hi>-man to the <hi>Palm-tree,</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> the <hi>Old</hi> man to the <hi>Almond-tree,</hi> and <hi>Eſay</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> man to the <hi>Cedaer,</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the <hi>Poore</hi> man to the <hi>Firre-tree; Dauid</hi> compareth the <hi>wicked</hi> man to the <hi>Bay-tree,</hi> and the <hi>good</hi> man to the <hi>Oliue-tree,</hi> among the reſt, and aboue the reſt euer <hi>flouriſhing.</hi> It was the <hi>conceit</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that the <hi>Doue</hi> brought this <hi>Oliue</hi> branch from <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> ſurely, <hi>whenceſoeuer,</hi> or <hi>howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer</hi> it came, it was a <hi>bleſſed token,</hi> and euer <hi>ſince</hi> the <hi>Oliue</hi> branch hath beene the <hi>Embleme</hi> of a <hi>bleſsing;</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> is that <hi>man</hi> that may beare an <hi>Oliue</hi> branch, in all the <hi>waues</hi> of this <hi>trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome world,</hi> that may be as an <hi>Oliue</hi> tree, <hi>ſtedfaſt</hi> in <hi>faith, ioyfull</hi> through <hi>hope,</hi> and <hi>rooted</hi> in <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and can thinke his <hi>Proſperity</hi> enough to <hi>liue</hi> out of the <hi>noyſe</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> as farre from <hi>ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi> as <hi>burning,</hi> and when <hi>heauenly contentments</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15629:18"/>haue poſſeſſed his <hi>Soule,</hi> hee looketh <hi>downe</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth <hi>diſpleaſedly,</hi> as the <hi>region</hi> of his <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> and <hi>baniſhment,</hi> ſtill praying for the <hi>proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> vpon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as our Royall <hi>Prophet</hi> now doth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>Now,</hi> the laſt Circumſtance.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Pſalme</hi> was made by <hi>Dauid,</hi> when hee was firſt <hi>inueſted</hi> into his <hi>Kingdome.</hi> Of all other <hi>perſons</hi> it concernes <hi>Kings</hi> to <hi>pray,</hi> &amp; of all other <hi>times,</hi> at their firſt <hi>entrance</hi> to their <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> begun their <hi>Rule</hi> with the <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>Prayer:</hi> The <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of a <hi>priuate</hi> man is his <hi>owne;</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> the whole <hi>worlds;</hi> his <hi>words</hi> are <hi>Maximes,</hi> his <hi>actions examples,</hi> his <hi>examples rules. Dauid,</hi> both <hi>priuately</hi> alone, and <hi>publikely</hi> in the Congregation, <hi>prepareth</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to prayer, in this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and the <hi>people</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked by their Kings example, pray for the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance,</hi> and long life of their <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> That God may <hi>diſtribute</hi> to the King <hi>gifts</hi> proportionable to his <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> that the <hi>head</hi> may <hi>enioy</hi> all the <hi>ſenſes</hi> of the whole body, that the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Iudges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heraclit.</note> and <hi>Lawes,</hi> &amp; all, may flouriſh; for as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus</hi> obſerueth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The King is the Image of God,</hi> the <hi>Iudge</hi> is the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> the <hi>worke</hi> of the <hi>Iudge,</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Law.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> had eſpeciall <hi>reaſon</hi> to pray, at this his <hi>Inauguration;</hi> for hee knew a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> warre was in hand, the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> were his deadly <hi>enemies,</hi> hee had beene among <hi>them,</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15629:18"/>knew <hi>them,</hi> and was now to make prouiſion <hi>against them.</hi> And therefore, as <hi>Numa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lor in Pſ. <hi>44.</hi> p. <hi>915.</hi>
               </note> when a rumor of <hi>Warre</hi> was raiſed; <hi>Sacrificabo,</hi> ſaith hee, I will ſacrifice; ſo, when <hi>Dauid</hi> foreſeeth this <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>forraigne enemies,</hi> hee <hi>betaketh</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto prayer. But I muſt leaue <hi>Dauid</hi> at his <hi>Prayer,</hi> and conclude with <hi>our times: Time</hi> is the <hi>concluſion</hi> of all things. <hi>Lord ſend now proſperity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if wee looke vpon our <hi>times,</hi> vpon this <hi>ſad, ſwift, ſpeedy</hi> time, feathered with <hi>flying houres,</hi> vpon this fatall <hi>Yeare;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec. Epiſt. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Menſis olim Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca, nunc annus eſt.</hi> This whole Yeare hath beene compoſed of the <hi>fall of the leafe,</hi> and <hi>Winter.</hi> O yee Mountaines of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> how many noble and <hi>valiant</hi> haue fallen this <hi>yeare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. of <hi>Richmond.</hi> E. of <hi>Dorſet.</hi> D. of <hi>Lennox.</hi> E. of <hi>Notingh.</hi> E. of <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and his Son. L. <hi>Belfoſt.</hi> M. <hi>Hamilton.</hi>
               </note> they that were <hi>louely</hi> and <hi>pleaſant</hi> in their <hi>liues,</hi> ſwifter then <hi>Eagles,</hi> ſtronger then <hi>Lyons:</hi> How many noble <hi>Families</hi> haue beene like the <hi>naked twigs</hi> of <hi>Winter,</hi> ſhiuering all for <hi>cold,</hi> and dropping downe their <hi>teares</hi> abundantly? How many of the choyce <hi>Peeres</hi> and <hi>Pearles</hi> hath <hi>Death</hi> ſtolne out of the <hi>Coronet</hi> of our <hi>Nobility?</hi> How many poore <hi>Firre-trees</hi> may <hi>mourne,</hi> for their <hi>Cedars</hi> bee fallen? And is not this an ill <hi>boading prodigious time,</hi> wherin with <hi>hearts,</hi> and <hi>tongues,</hi> and <hi>teares,</hi> and <hi>prayers</hi> wee had need to <hi>crye, Lord, now ſend proſperity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Caſt your <hi>watry eyes</hi> vpon the <hi>fatality</hi> of this <hi>bloody Moneth,</hi> and not to looke vpon the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Triumph</hi> of <hi>Funerall Solemnities</hi> in <hi>March;</hi>
               <note place="margin">March. 24.</note> remember how in this <hi>Moneth</hi> wee were depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of <hi>bleſſed</hi> Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the <hi>Paragon</hi> of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15629:19"/>
               <hi>mortall Princes,</hi> the <hi>Woman after Gods own heart,</hi> the <hi>Virgin-Queene</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> the enuy of the <hi>Infidell</hi> World; who came ſo neere vnto the <hi>bleſſed Virgin Mary,</hi> that ſhee was <hi>borne</hi> vpon the <hi>Vigil</hi> of her <hi>birth,</hi> and <hi>dyed</hi> vpon the <hi>Vigil</hi> of her <hi>Annunciation:</hi> Remember the <hi>ſable</hi> time ſince the Death of the Royall <hi>Vine</hi> of this Kingdome,<note place="margin">Martij <hi>20. 1618.</hi> die Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> 
               <hi>Queene Anne</hi> in this very moneth; a <hi>Queene</hi> not <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> not <hi>factious,</hi> not <hi>tyrannous;</hi> but <hi>religious</hi> to her God, and moſt <hi>gracious</hi> to all the Subiects of this <hi>Land,</hi> and her well <hi>deſeruing</hi> ſeruants: Not a <hi>Lioneſſe</hi> hunting for the prey as <hi>Iezabel,</hi> or a <hi>Typer</hi> greedy of the ſpoile as <hi>Athaliah;</hi> but a <hi>ſweetly tempered</hi> &amp; <hi>Royall Lady,</hi> whom <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> crowned, and <hi>Glory</hi> hath made Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and God,<note place="margin">Martij <hi>23. 1618.</hi> die mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> in this Moneth not many yeares ſince, tooke from vs, as one, of <hi>whom the world was not worthy of,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Inter foelices &amp; foeliciſsima quondam</l>
               <l>Regis enim Conjux, Eilia, Mater, erat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Remember the fatall ſickneſſe at <hi>Royſton,</hi> when that acute and violent <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> ſeazed vpon <hi>our Royall</hi> Soueraigne, in this very moneth, when our <hi>feares</hi> encreaſed with the <hi>minuts,</hi> and euery <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger</hi> was as one of the <hi>Chorus</hi> in a <hi>Tragedie;</hi> as <hi>Iobs meſsengers,</hi> euery one adding to the <hi>ſorrowes</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſad times,</hi> and when</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Duxiſſet mox fila ſecanda ſorores,</l>
               <l>Non ſic eſt viſum Sceptris: —</l>
            </q>
            <p>Our <hi>Royall Hezekias</hi> recouered miraculouſly to Gods <hi>glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 4.20.</note> the good of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15629:19"/>and great comfort of all his good <hi>Subiects.</hi> But <hi>alas,</hi> our ſinnes haue fought againſt our <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>now Death</hi> the <hi>ledge</hi> of all mens <hi>liues,</hi> that ſets vpon men with <hi>ſtealing ſteps,</hi> &amp; <hi>inſenſible degrees, threatens</hi> a final <hi>areſt</hi> vpon our <hi>Royal</hi> Maſter. The breath of our <hi>noſtrils,</hi> the <hi>Anointed of the Lord is taken in the ſnare, of whom we ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam 4 20.</note> 
               <hi>Vnder his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow we ſhall liue. The Crowne is falling from our head, woe vnto vs that we haue ſinned; for this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>our heart is faint, for theſe things our eyes are dimme.</hi> O thou God of <hi>Iacob</hi> defend him; <hi>ſend him help from thy Sanctuarie, &amp; ſtrengthen him out of Zion, for thou Lord remaineſt for euer and euer, thy Throne from generation to generation, Lord we beſeech thee ſaue now, Lord we beſeech thee ſend now proſperitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a diuine Canticle of a ſweet <hi>Singer</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> vpon his Maieſties laſt <hi>recouery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Goodwine Deane of Chriſt. Church.</note> why this <hi>Moneth</hi> was ſo <hi>infeſtuous</hi> to our <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Tu Martem odiſti, Mars odit pacis amantem,</l>
               <l>Hinc tantae clades, hinc tot conamina Martis,</l>
            </q>
            <p>It was <hi>about</hi> this very time of the <hi>yeare</hi> ſay ſome that the firſt foundation of <hi>Venice</hi> was layed,<note place="margin">Hoſp. de Orig. F</note> ſure I am we ſtand <hi>here vpon</hi> a <hi>watry</hi> foundation, the <hi>water-Springs</hi> of our owne <hi>teares</hi> are able to <hi>ſinke</hi> vs: The computation of ſome is <hi>approued,</hi> who hold, that the <hi>world</hi> was created about this very time, and I remember the firſt <hi>worke in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was that the Spirit of God moued vpon the face of the waters.</hi> We are now <hi>labouring</hi> vnder a <hi>new Creation, the ſame bleſſed ſpirit of God moue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our watry faces, &amp; dry vp the teares of our eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the <hi>Liturgie</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> that teacheth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15629:20"/>vs, that in <hi>the midſt</hi> of <hi>life</hi> wee are in <hi>death.</hi> But <hi>bleſſed be our God in the midſt of death we are now in life;</hi> there is preſent a <hi>gracious Doue</hi> with an <hi>O liue branch,</hi> that ſhall <hi>bring comfortable newes to our world,</hi> and the <hi>waters ſhall ceaſe:</hi> I neuer was like to that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that baſe flatterer, who is,<note place="margin">In vita Conſtan.</note> as <hi>Aurelius Victor</hi> well obſerued, <hi>ſorex &amp; tinea Palatij:</hi> I know his Princely <hi>diſpoſition</hi> hath euer <hi>hated</hi> a <hi>Paraſite</hi> as the worſt <hi>Traitor;</hi> God keepe <hi>two miſchiefes</hi> euer from within the <hi>ſmoake of his Court, Flatterie</hi> and <hi>Treacherie;</hi> the <hi>Inquitie</hi> of the <hi>times</hi> may make vs <hi>feare</hi> theſe, not his <hi>gracious inclination:</hi> but this I may ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> ſeldome <hi>euer haue thoſe yeares promiſed, ſeldome haue performed ſo much, and we haue ſeen enough to make vs think we can neuer be enough thankfull to God for him.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member an obſeruation of an <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fift,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Knolls in the Ger. Hiſtor.</note> who being borne vpon <hi>Mathias</hi> day, and hauing an <hi>Elder brother aliue,</hi> his Grandmother applied by a <hi>Phrophecy,</hi> that of <hi>Mathias</hi> election vnto <hi>Charles</hi> the new borne <hi>Prince,</hi> that as the <hi>Lot</hi> fell vpon <hi>Mathias,</hi> though <hi>laſt in place,</hi> ſo the <hi>Lot</hi> of the Empire <hi>ſhould fall</hi> from the <hi>Elder brother</hi> vpon Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> though laſt in birth. The like <hi>Lot</hi> is now fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vnto your <hi>Princely Highneſſe,</hi> and my <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> be, that all your dayes may bee like the two <hi>Saints daies</hi> of this moneth, <hi>Foelix</hi> and <hi>Perpetua,</hi> that when your <hi>Royall Father</hi> ſhall paſſe <hi>à Corona ad Coronam,</hi> as it was one of the <hi>Diuine medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> propoſed this <hi>morning</hi> to his Maieſty by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15629:20"/>that moſt honorable <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and that <hi>he ſhall</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change this <hi>mortall</hi> for a Crowne of <hi>immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Lord Keeper.</note> that the ſpirit of your <hi>gracious Father</hi> may be <hi>doubled</hi> vpon your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> as the ſpirit of <hi>Elias</hi> was vpon <hi>Eliſha, that true Religion may flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh vnder you;</hi> and that you may <hi>ride on</hi> in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty proſperouſly, becauſe of truth, and meekeneſſe, and righteouſnes:</hi> That you may <hi>ride on</hi> in <hi>truth,</hi> for <hi>State</hi> without <hi>truth,</hi> is like <hi>Pride</hi> without <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,</hi> an vmbrageous <hi>Pageant</hi> for <hi>ſight</hi> not for <hi>ſeruice.</hi> That you may <hi>ride on</hi> in <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> for <hi>truth</hi> without <hi>Maieſtie</hi> is like a <hi>Talent</hi> hid in a <hi>banke,</hi> or a <hi>Candle</hi> vnder a <hi>buſhell:</hi> That you may <hi>ride on</hi> in <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and <hi>meekeneſse,</hi> for <hi>Maieſtie</hi> without <hi>weekneſſe,</hi> is like <hi>greatneſſe</hi> without <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> the <hi>Politicians Character,</hi> but the <hi>Peoples curſe:</hi> That you may <hi>ride on</hi> with <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and <hi>meekeneſſe</hi> and <hi>proſperitie,</hi> for <hi>Maieſtie</hi> without <hi>proſperity</hi> is like <hi>Heauen</hi> without a <hi>ſun,</hi> or the <hi>Summer</hi> without a <hi>Harueſt.</hi> That you may <hi>ride on</hi> in <hi>Maieſty, truth, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>proſperity</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> for <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi> without <hi>righteouſneſse,</hi> is like <hi>beauty</hi> without <hi>honeſtie,</hi> a <hi>wanton dead ſoule</hi> in a <hi>painted ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher:</hi> but when your Canopie of <hi>Maieſtie</hi> is <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported</hi> by <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>meekneſſe,</hi> and <hi>proſperitie</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe, Bleſsings</hi> and <hi>prayers</hi> will be ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon <hi>you,</hi> God, euen your <hi>owne</hi> God ſhall giue you his <hi>bleſsing,</hi> and God, euen our <hi>owne</hi> God ſhall ſend vs <hi>proſperitie;</hi> Which the Lord <hi>grant,</hi> for his <hi>mercie,</hi> for his <hi>promiſe,</hi> for his <hi>Zion,</hi> for his <hi>Sonnes ſake Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
